Two years ago, I decided to publicly manage an
兩年前我決定公開運作一個
experimental investment portfolio
實驗性的投資組合
I named it Hi5
取名叫做Hi5
The Hi5 portfolio started in August 2023
Hi5組合從2023年8月開始
It began with 500,000 Canadian dollars
從50萬加元開始
After 22 months of continuous investment
經過22個月的持續的投入
plus the effect of market growth
再加上市場放大的效應
by June of this year
到今年的6月
the portfolio's net value
這個組合的淨值
has surpassed 1 million Canadian dollars
已經跨越了100萬加元
This important milestone
這個重要的關卡
The portfolio's compound growth rate
組合的複合增長率
is also close to 12%
也接近12%
My idea behind the experimental portfolio is simple
我做實驗組合的想法很簡單
I want to prove with a real example that
就是想用一個實際的案例來證明
This is for us ordinary investors
這是我們普通投資者
The easiest way to build wealth
最容易積累財富的方式
If you watched my video from two years ago
如果你看過兩年前我這支影片
but didn't take any action
卻沒有采取任何行動
I think you should seriously reconsider
我認為你應該好好想想了
This asset growth curve
這條資產增值曲線
was supposed to be yours
本來應該是屬於你的
Achieving this result is actually very simple
要實現這個成績也非常的簡單
First, keep investing consistently
首先就是持續的投入
Regardless of market ups and downs
不論市場漲跌
I invest according to plan every month
我每個月都按計劃投入
I have a clear set of rules
我有一套明確的規則
A fixed amount is invested each month
每個月有固定的投入金額
Based on how much the market drops
根據市場下跌的幅度
Next, choose the right time to enter
再來選擇進入的時機
Then, stick to this set of rules
然後就是堅持這套規則
This set of rules
這套規則
Simply put
簡單來說
is called DCA plus BTD
就是叫做DCA加BTD
I have explained in another video
我在另外一支影片當中
in detail
有詳細介紹過
the advantages of this investment method
這種投資方式的優勢
The DCA plus BTD approach
DCA加BTD的方式
allows me to invest more during market downturns
它讓我能夠在市場下跌的過程當中
putting in more capital
投入更多
and then during market upswings
然後在市場上漲的過程當中
to grow my capital
把我的資本放大
This investment strategy
這種投資方式
is the key to success
能夠成功的核心
It's about finding stocks that keep rising
就在於找到持續上漲的標的
That's why investing in the US stock market
所以說投資美股市場
is a key part of this strategy
是這一套規則的一個關鍵所在
I often see people online discussing
我經常看到一些網友討論
and they always worry that the US stock market
他們總是擔心美股
will crash and never recover
跌下去就起不來了
Of course
當然了
the main reason might be the media
主要原因可能是因為媒體
which loves to hype up disasters
最喜歡渲染這種災難
Creating anxiety is a huge business in itself
製造焦慮本身是一門巨大的生意
So in my videos
所以我的影片
I aim to help you ease that anxiety
我希望能夠幫助你消除焦慮
In the long run
從長遠來看
the US stock market will definitely go up
美股必定是向上走的
This is a rigged game
這是一個被操縱了的遊戲
You could say it is
你可以認為它是
because of an oversupply of money
因為貨幣供應過量
Or that there's just too much money
或者說是錢太多導致的
But on a deeper level
但是深層次意義上說
this is the inevitable result of capitalism and vote-driven politics
這是資本主義與選票政治的必然結果
Goldman Sachs has statistics showing
高盛有一項統計數據顯示
the richest 1% in the U.S
美國最富有的1%的階層
own more than 50% of the stocks
擁有超過50%的股票
Meanwhile, the bottom 50%
而底層的50%階層
own just 1% of the stocks
僅僅擁有1%的股票
Think about it
你想想
Who are the ones least wanting the stock market to crash?
最不希望股市崩潰的是哪些人
Why are you so worried about a bear market?
為什麼你那麼擔心熊市
And those who are the wealthiest of the wealthy
而那些最頂級富有的那些人
confidently put more than 50% of their assets
卻安心把自己資產50%以上
into the stock market
放在股市裡
So
所以啊
if you can clearly understand this issue
你能夠想清楚這個問題
investing becomes very simple
投資就變得非常簡單了
Whenever the stock market drops
每當股市下跌
corrects
修正
especially when a crash happens every few years
特別是每隔幾年就會來一次崩盤
at times like these
這樣的這個時候
this is actually an opportunity to accelerate your wealth growth
這其實是加速你財富升級的機會
Because the market will eventually recover
因為市場最終會恢復的
and ultimately reach new highs
最終會創新高的
This is an essential characteristic of the U.S. stock market
這是美股市場的一個本質特徵
But please remember
不過請記住
Here, I am referring to the major U.S. stock market indices
我這裡指的是美股的大盤指數
Some stocks have fallen
某一些股票跌下去
They might never recover
可能就再也起不來了
Data from JP Morgan shows
JP摩根的數據顯示
Between 1980 and 2020
在1980年到2020年間
44% of the companies in the Russell 3000 index
羅素3000指數當中44%的公司
experienced catastrophic losses
經歷了災難性損失
Catastrophic loss means
所謂災難性損失
the stock price fell from its peak to its lowest point
就是指股價從最高峰跌到谷底
It dropped more than 70%
跌了70%以上
And it never recovered
並且沒有能夠恢復
It never reached a new high again
沒有能夠再創新高
In the healthcare sector
在醫療行業
In the technology and consumer discretionary sectors
科技和可選消費行業當中
Catastrophic losses occurred
發生災難性損失的
This probability is the highest
這種概率是最高的
During this period
在這期間
42% of the stocks in the Russell 3000 index
羅素3000指數當中42%的股票
generated negative absolute returns
產生了負的絕對回報
66% of the stocks underperformed the market
66%的股票表現跑輸市場
Only 10% of the stocks
只有10%的股票
were able to outperform the market during this period
在這期間能夠跑贏市場
And achieved cumulative returns of 500%
並且獲得累計500%
or more
或者更多的回報
Additionally, in the past 5 years
另外在過去5年當中
the top 20% best-performing stocks
表現最佳的20%的股票
in the following 10 years
在接下來的10年中
had a median cumulative return relative to the market of
它們相對於市場的
Median cumulative return is -17.8%
中位數累計回報是 -17.8%
Among these stocks, 60%
這一類股票當中有60%的股票
It underperforms the market
是跑輸市場的
In short
簡而言之一句話
If you hope to grow your wealth by picking a few stocks
如果你希望通過選擇少數幾隻股票
to achieve wealth growth
來實現財富增值的目的
statistically speaking
從統計學意義上來看
you are very likely to fail
這大概率是要失敗的
So
所以啊
accept that you are an ordinary person
承認自己是一個普通的人
and invest in index ETFs in the US stock market
投資美股市場的指數ETF
Especially ETFs with a survival-of-the-fittest mechanism
尤其是有優勝劣汰機制的ETF
Consistent, long-term investment
長期的持續的投入
these three points are the easiest ways for ordinary investors
這三點是我們普通投資者
to steadily build wealth
最容易積累財富的方式
and also the most effective
也是最有效的方式
The US stock market's long-term compound return over 100 years
美股市場100年的長期複合回報率
It's roughly around 10%
差不多就是10%左右
It doesn't seem high
看上去不高
But let's look at a set of data
但是我們來看一組數據
From December 31, 1992 to September 30, 2022
在1992年12月31日至2022年9月30日
During this period
這個期間
in the U.S. market
美國市場上的
among actively managed stock funds
主動管理型股票基金當中
59% of the funds did not survive
有59%的基金未能存活
They either closed down
他們要麼是關閉了
or were merged
要麼是被兼併了
30% of the funds survived
有30%的基金存活了
but underperformed the S&amp;P 500 index
但是表現不如標普500指數
Only 10% of the funds
只有10%的基金
survived and outperformed the S&amp;P 500 index
存活並且表現超越標普500指數
This shows
這說明
A 10% long-term investment return
10%的長期投資回報率
is very, very hard to achieve
是非常非常不容易做到的
How to build wealth with around a 10% return
怎樣在10%左右的回報率上面去積累財富
is a question every investor
是我們每一位投資者
must seriously consider
必須思考的問題
The more you dismiss this 10% return
你越是看不上這10%的回報率
and act overly proud
你越是自命不凡
the harder it will be for you to build wealth
你就越是無法積累財富
My Hi5 portfolio
我這個Hi5組合
is like a mirror
它就像是一面鏡子
Checking it every once in a while
你每隔一段時間過來照一照
is beneficial
是有好處的
The trading rules for this portfolio are very simple
這個組合的交易規則非常的簡單
All the trading details are fully transparent
交易細節也都是完全公開的
I believe in what I can achieve
我相信我能做到的事情
You can do it too
你也能做到
Of course
當然了
There is no perfect strategy in the world
世界上沒有完美的策略
The Hi5 portfolio itself also needs to go through natural selection
Hi5組合本身也需要優勝劣汰
So the purpose of today's video
所以今天這個影片的
is another goal
另外一個目的
which is to share with everyone
就是跟大家分享
the upcoming adjustment plan for this portfolio
這個組合接下來的調整方案
According to the portfolio's trading rules
按照組合的交易規則
in the upcoming August
在接下來的8月份
when condition 1 is met
在滿足條件1
or condition 2 is met
或者條件2的時候
I will carry out the portfolio's annual rebalancing
我就會實施組合的年度再平衡操作
Among the 5 ETFs currently held
目前持有的5隻 ETF當中
MOAT will be replaced by SPMO
MOAT將會被替換為SPMO
No changes will be made to the other ETFs for now
其他的ETF暫時不做變化
Let me explain here
這裡解釋一下
What does rebalancing mean?
什麼叫做再平衡
The Hi5 portfolio consists of 5 ETFs
由於Hi5組合5隻 ETF
The initial setup is equal weighting
初始的設定是等權重的
That means
也就是說
the market value of the 5 ETFs is equal
5隻 ETF的市值相等
And every time I add more investment
並且我每一次增加投入的時候
I do it based on the equal weighting principle
也都是按照等權重的原則進行的
After running for a year
經過了一年的運行之後
some ETFs have risen a lot
有的ETF漲的多
while others have risen less
有的ETF漲的少
So I need to
於是我需要
rebalance the portfolio every year to
每年讓這個組合重新回到
bring the 5 ETFs back to equal market value
5隻 ETF市值相等的狀態
This operation
這個操作
is called rebalancing
就叫做再平衡
Specifically
具體來說
in August
就是在8月份
when the conditions are met
滿足條件的時候
I need to take the current portfolio's
我需要將當前組合當中
total market value
這個總市值
add the amount to be invested in August
再加上8月份
需要投入的金額
需要投入的金額
then divide by five to get
然後除以5就得到了
the market value allocated to each ETF
每一隻ETF需要分配的市值
ETFs exceeding the allocated market value
超出分配市值的ETF
need to have some shares sold
需要賣出一部分
ETFs below the allocated market value
沒有達到分配市值的ETF
need to have some shares bought
需要再買入一部分
to make up for
來補足
let these 5 ETFs
讓這5只ETF
return to an equal-weighted status
重新回到等權重的狀態
this process is called rebalancing
這個操作就是再平衡操作
the ones to be replaced
將要被替換掉的
MOAT will be completely sold off
MOAT將會全部賣出
and then SPMO will be purchased
然後再買入SPMO
why replace MOAT with SPMO
為什麼要用SPMO來替換MOAT
SPMO is a momentum model
SPMO是一個動量模型
in short
簡而言之
it selects from the S&amp;P 500 index
就是選取標普500指數當中
the best-performing stocks in terms of price
股價表現最好的股票
MOAT tracks the index compiled by Morningstar
MOAT是跟蹤晨星公司編制的
the Wide Moat Index
寬護城河指數
it is based on company fundamentals
是一個基於企業基本面
A model for stock selection
來選股的一個模型
In the rules for these two ETFs
這兩隻ETF的編制規則當中
there is a survival of the fittest mechanism
都是有優勝劣汰機制的
Using SPMO to replace MOAT
用SPMO去替換MOAT
logically speaking
從邏輯上說
it means using the market's survival of the fittest mechanism
就是用市場的優勝劣汰機制
to replace the fundamental survival of the fittest rule
來去替換基本面的優勝劣汰法則
Let the market decide who is the best
讓市場來決定誰是最好的
From August 2023 until now
從2023年8月到現在
looking at overall performance
整體表現上看
SPMO has performed much better than MOAT
SPMO是要遠好於MOAT
And during the market downturn in March this year
並且在今年3月份的
in the falling market
下跌行情當中
MOAT actually dropped before the S&amp;P 500 index did
MOAT實際上是先於標普500指數下跌的
The overall drop is about the same as SPMO
總的跌幅與SPMO差不多
But the recovery process
但是恢復的過程
But it is far behind SPMO
卻要遠遠落後於SPMO
From this, it’s clear
由此可見
that MOAT’s risk-return ratio
MOAT的風險回報比
is not as good as SPMO’s
是不如SPMO的
In other words
也就是說
MOAT hasn’t achieved
MOAT並沒有達到
the kind of
我預期的那種
defensive goal I expected
防守型的目的
It falls just as much when dropping
跌的時候沒少跌
but doesn’t perform well when rising
漲的時候又不給力
So
所以說
in the upcoming adjustment plan
接下去的調整計劃當中
it will be replaced
它將被替換掉
I also hope this adjustment will work
我也希望這一次調整操作
It can properly increase the compound return rate of the Hi5 portfolio
能夠適當提高Hi5組合的複合回報率
I want to run it for a while first and see
我想先運行一段時間看看
If it doesn't meet the expected goals
如果說達不到預期的目標
then next year
會在明年
we will make adjustments again
我們再來做調整
In short
總而言之
constant adjustments through survival of the fittest
優勝劣汰不斷的調整
continuous survival of the fittest
不斷的優勝劣汰
this is the way to survive in the financial market
這是金融市場的生存之道
Anyway
總之
my investment principle is
我的投資原則
to make the easiest money possible
是賺最容易賺到的錢
and to accumulate wealth in the simplest way
用最簡單的方式去積累財富
Alright
好
That's all I have to say
就說這麼多
I'm Lao Lei
我是老雷
See you in the next video
我們下支影片再見
Bye-bye
拜拜